hello and welcome it's September 20th
2020 23. we're at the Active inference
Institute in the course active inference
for the social sciences and here with
MAO Albertson who will be presenting
today on Norm scripts and Linguistics
under active inference so thank you Mao
to you
awesome so hi everyone
um as uh last time there was a
presentation on semiotics and semantics
I won't dig too far into Linguistics but
I'll touch on it at the end of the
course
so
what are we going to do in this module
we're going to explore the concept of
active inference and its relevance to
social norms and human decision making
as you will
um have seen in the previous classes
active inference is a theoretical
framework that seeks to explain how
organisms including humans engage with
their environment to minimize
uncertainty and maintain their internal
States we're not going to dig into these
Concepts too too much because I assume
they have been
um previously explained at length
however I will explain how they connect
to social phenomena
so this framework has significant
implications for understanding social
behavior as it can help explain how
individuals conform to social norms and
make decisions based on the expectations
of others
we'll delve into the role of active
inference in human societies emphasizing
how humans and other organisms
constantly seek to minimize their
uncertainty about the World by updating
their beliefs and taking actions to
maintain a stable internal state
this is a crucial process for survival
it allows individuals to predict and
adapt to their environment in the
context of human societies
active inference plays a critical role
in explaining how individuals navigate
complex social situations conform to
social expectations and make decisions
that align with their beliefs and values
furthermore
we'll explore the concept of beyondic
value within active inference which
refers to the value of attributed to
actions based on their adherence to
social norms and expectations
by adhering to social norms individuals
can minimize the uncertainty associated
with their actions and maintain a sense
of predictability and stability in their
social environment
so together all these insights will
provide you with a comprehensive
understanding of the complex interplay
between active inference social norms
and human decision making
so let's Dive In
we'll start by introducing a
philosophical framework building on the
framework of active inference in
activism offers us a complementary lens
to understand the dynamic and contextual
nature of social cognition so while
active inference provides the
computational underpinnings for
understanding social norms and
decisional making we still need to
Anchor ourselves within a larger
theoretical framework inactivism
enriches this perspective by emphasizing
the Practical and developmental aspects
of social understanding
so what is inactivism
if it hasn't been introduced before
inactivism is a philosophical stance
that extends Beyond traditional theories
of cognition emphasizing the role of
inter interactions and relational
Dynamics in shaping both individual and
social cognition
it argues that cognition is a dynamic
real-time fluid and contextual social
action
you can read more about this uh in
ineshipolito's texts and Thomas van s in
2022.
generative models and hermeneutics
serve as a cognitive structure and
framework for interpretation
respectively
these elements are continuously updated
based on social interactions and signals
thereby facilitating effective
communication and understanding
hermeneutics provides a theoretical
framework for interpreting social
signals and cues crucial for Effective
social interactions
so perminutics allows for a nuanced
understanding of contextually
constituted meaning
it goes beyond the conventional notion
of self-contained objects to explore the
deeper contextual meanings in behavior
and cognition
hermeneutics offers a way to analyze
social action that goes beyond
positivist and humanist approaches by
fusing the conceptual schemes of the
Observer and the social actor
it complements inactivism by providing
the interpretive framework that are
continuously updated through social
interactions enriching our understanding
of cognition as Dynamic real-time and
cognition and contextual
in the realm of social cognition
inactivism
introduces the concept of generalized
synchronization
which
allows for a nuanced understanding of
how social interactions mutually
influence cognitive processes
the relationship between individual
beliefs and social expectations is
complex it's fundamentally shaped by our
interactions with the others and the
world
we thus see that meaning is
co-constituted by the individual and the
environment
if we adopt an actress and hermeneutics
approach we find the philosophical
foundations that lead into a
comprehensive overview of the
intersection with social cognition
if you want more references to read
about these topics you can ask me at the
end of the class and I can send you a
few
so it's essential to note however that
there are some criticisms uh that point
out the limitations of inactivism in
explaining social cognition
one of the key criticism is that current
articulations of inactivism are not yet
up to the task when it comes to
explaining complex social interactions
despite these criticisms inactivism
provides a consistent epistemology for a
psychology that is intrinsically social
looking forward the field of inactivism
and social cognition is right for
exploration and would benefit from a
deeper connection to active influence
there has been such research so
researchers uh like Maxwell ramstead has
developed a concept of inactive
inference which offers a promising
Avenue for integrating inactivism and
active inference
he's research aligns with full
psychology and suggests that these
Frameworks can coexist and enrich our
understandings of social cognition
future other directions can involve for
instance integrating inactivism with
other recognitive theories and exploring
its applicability applicability in real
world social scenarios through its
connection to active inference we can
make accurate and testable predictions
so while inactivism now provides us with
a foundational understanding of
cognition and social interaction the
concept of agency further enriches this
understanding by introducing more
philosophical perspectives that align
with or diverge from inactivism so
we can build on top of an activism
through the notion of agency
so we will now focus on the key issue of
inactivism which is how does agency
emerge how do things self-organize
um through their interaction with the
environment why are they not fully
determined
how can we account for agency in a
system where effectively
self-organization is seen as some degree
of determined by the materiality of the
agentence environment
agency is a complex construct that has
been explored through a multitude of
philosophical and scientific Frameworks
one prominent approach is the inactive
affordance-based perspective
which underscores the centrality of the
I can notion in shaping both cognitive
processes and behavioral outcomes
so Maxwell ramstead again substantiates
this perspective and resonates with the
research conducted by brunberg in 2018.
it posits for instance that agency is
far from being a mere passive State
rather it involves active Dynamic
engagement with the environment
current investigations in this domain
are being for instance continued by
researchers like radi pitlia who is
working on connecting properly uh the
the psychological phenomenon of agency
in uh active inference modeling
in parallel Tom holds you Invasion
models conceptualize active inference as
a Bayesian process aimed at minimizing
prediction error
this model finds support in the work of
Cal and comp and suggests that agency is
an active Endeavor to aligns sensory
inputs with internal predictions thereby
fostering a sense of control and
self-efficacy
the cybernetic interpretations offers a
more mechanistic lens focusing on
control mechanism in homeostasis
in this view agency is not just about
accurate predictions but also about
maintaining a balanced State through
Dynamic interpretations interaction
sorry with the environment
recent studies highlight the
significance of performance-based
inferences in shaping our sense of
agency
that approach suggested the congruence
between our actions and their expected
outcomes plays a pivotal role in
strengthening or weakening our sense of
agency
so collectively these diverse
interpretations serve as intellectual
Bridges connecting the domains of
philosophy Psychology and computational
Neuroscience
they offer complementary insights that
enrich our understanding of agency
thereby contributing to the broader
discourse on inactivism and its
application in understanding complex
cognitive and social phenomena
so how is Agents agency extended
deep temporal models and the concept of
agency both focus on the minimization of
uncertainty and the optimization of
decision making
deep temporal models provide a
computational framework that can model
the complex
time-dependent patterns of behavior and
cognition
offering insights into how an agency is
exercised in Dynamic social contexts
in the context of our overall goal of
understanding scripts through active
inference combining deep temporal models
with theories of agency allows us to
create more nuanced and predictive
models of how individuals navigate
social norms and make decisions through
goal-directed actions across different
scales of concern
in social cognition deep temporal models
help individuals anticipate and adapt to
changes in their social environment
across time skills that go beyond what
would be considered simply reactive
thereby reducing uncertainty and
enhancing decision making
an individual can plan an extend agency
beyond the current moment
so in the realm of planning algorithms
deep temporal models allow us for a
theoretical foundation for optimality
especially when resources are limited
they enable State abstraction and
cognitive control essential elements in
hierarchical planning
deep Temple models also constitute to
contribute to various cognitive
processes such as action understanding
and language processing which we will
discuss later
they can be interpreted and integrated
into deep reinforcement learning
algorithms to develop socially aware
navigation policies
deep temporal models thus serve as a
computational again bridge between the
neural mechanisms of action
understanding and the cognitive
processes that give rise to agency
so what might be potentially
neural mechanism that allows us to
connect deep temporal models to
um social interactions
this is where we bring in the insights
from neuroneuron systems and active
inference
this way we can have a more
comprehensive models that only predicts
but explains how individuals exercise
agency and complex social landscapes
here mirror neurons serve as a neural
Cornerstone for social cognition
firing not only during the execution of
an action but also during the
observation of that same action
performed by another
these specialized neurons are Central to
The Continuous updating of internal
models of the environment
including the actions and intentions of
others
they minimize uncertainty and facilitate
navigation through complex social
Landscapes allowing us for smoother
social interactions and more effective
communication
so here the Deep temporal models are
hierarchical generative models that
offer a computational framework
and these models are Adept at handling
the complexities of self-agency and
other agency
in the context of self-agency a deep
temporal models affords a high bias or
Precision to proprioceptive predictions
which gives us a nuanced understanding
of one's own actions
when observing another this bias is
adaptively suppressed enabling the
system to be flexible and context
sensitive
the interplay between mirror neurons and
deep temporal model is thus a compelling
area of research mirror neurons
contribute to the process of updating
internal models which is a core function
of uh deep temporal models
this synergistic relationship lasts for
more nuanced understanding of action
prediction
we can see a deep and significant
implication for long-term planning in
Social context The Continuous updating
of internal models facilitated by mirror
neurons and computationally powered here
through the Deep temporal models is
crucial for making complex decisions and
planning future social interactions
there's been Recent research that
indicates that our capacity to
understand actions extend beyond the
mirror neuron systems which involves the
activation of areas signaling unexpected
events
this adds another layer of complexity to
the already intricate interplay between
the neurons and the models which suggest
that our understanding of action
prediction and social cognition is far
from complete but is advancing rapidly
thanks to these integrated Frameworks
so given the ongoing research on mirror
neurons we have to consider how
computational models like deep temporal
models can offer a more nuanced
framework for studying these neural
mechanisms
so
let's try to think about
um some of the issues with mirror neuron
research
it's not without controversy some
critical reviews argue that there's no
compelling evidence supporting the role
of mirror neurons in action
understanding
others can suggest that mirror neurons
may be involved in lower level processes
of action perception but not in higher
level intention understanding
so we need more studies to control for
pre-motor contributions to action
perception and provide a clearer
definition of what is meant by action
understanding
this is particularly important as some
Research indicates that there may be no
proof that mirror neurons lead to action
understanding
this doesn't mean that it negates the
importance of these systems it means we
need more research to make sure that
they are in fact related to action
understanding
the functional properties of the mirror
neuron system indicates that action
understanding May primarily be based on
the motor cognition that under underpins
one's own capacity to act
so we will now consider how these neural
mechanisms can be integrated into
broader Frameworks like extended and
optimized active inference
so by doing so we can leverage
generative models to provide a more
nuanced understanding of action
perception prediction social cognition
and adapting behaviors to lead us to
scripts gender perspectives and cultural
affordances
we have expanded in time
now let's expand in space
extended and optimize active inference
represents a comprehensive framework
that Bridges between internal cognitive
processes and external environmental
interactions
generative models serve as the
Cornerstone extending beyond the
confines of an organism's brain and body
to incorporate external cognitive
resources such as Maps or written
language
this extension not only enhances the
efficiency and accuracy of these models
but also has practical implications in
various domains like social interactions
and language processing
if we think of a cognitive niche
um
the framework introduces key Dynamics
like selective Developmental and
organism Niche coordination
the Dynamics elucidate the intricate
relationship between organisms and their
environment
including the reciprocal effects of
environmental modifications and
selection pressures
in sequential Dynamics generative models
facilitate effective communication and
understanding
they allow us to see the emergence of
Behavioral and neurophysiological
correlates such as Theta gamma coupling
which we will discuss later in neural
activity which can be seen as an
emergent property of belief updating
under variational message passing
billing upon the foundational aspects of
extending and optimized active inference
it's crucial to delve into its specific
applications in Social contexts
when we optimize our generative models
through social scripts and Norms we can
see how extending active inference
serves as a practical tool for
navigating and modifying complex social
Landscapes aligning with the framework's
broader goals of cognitive Niche
Construction
so we can see that this integrates both
internal and external cognitive
resources to optimize the generative
model
scripts serve as a cognitive blueprint
that reduce the uncertainty and
facilitates successful social
interactions they're continuously
updated through adapted changing social
Landscapes they enhance the fluidity and
adaptability of social behaviors
social norms act as a macro level
behavioral expectation that shapes the
social environment and creates favorable
niches for human interactions
these Norms are internal representations
that help individuals navigate complex
social environments effectively
so here cognitive Niche Construction
involves active modification of the
environment to create those favorable
contexts
extended active inference takes us a
step further by allowing for the
optimization of generative models
creating environments that are not just
favorable but also harmonious
the comprehensive approach here has
implications that span from psychology
sociology artificial intelligence and
allows us to potentially set the stage
for future research and cognitive
science
so here we see that there's an
importance to optimizing internal models
for effect to effective social
interactions
so while extended active inference
focuses on the broader cognitive
architecture involving generative models
and social norms
here we zero in on the role of deontic
value and social Conformity providing a
more nuanced understanding of how
individuals adapt and shape their social
environment
so the concept of deontic value
refers to the value attributed to
actions based on their adherence to
social norms and expectations
it allows us to guide individual choices
when faced with a decision an individual
way the deontic value of potential
actions against other factors like
personal preferences beliefs
to determine the most appropriate course
of action
he'll just allow me one
so this ties us very nicely to the
notion of agency that we explored before
in regimes of Expectations by axle
constant we elaborate the deonta cues
enable the environment to learn about
the behavior of its inhabitants
effectively Outsourcing the epistemic
and pragmatic values of any Behavior
you can see that the extension of active
inference here takes on a whole other
meaning
so active inference allows for dynamic
adaptation enables the individual to
update their internal models better
anticipate and connect to their
environments such that the environment
and the individual mutually model each
other
the optic value here serves as a Common
Thread between active inference and
regimes of expectations
through these regimes of expectation and
active inference we'll achieve a better
understanding of social Conformity and
decision making
regimes of expectations centers on the
computational construct of deontic value
which we explained before
and aligns with the broader research on
social conformity
especially the winner takes all model
proposed by Frank in 2008.
social expectation here plays
significant role in shaping human
decisions and specifically social
Conformity act as a learning strategy
which is effective in on certain
environments
so now that we build on the foundational
role of deontic value in the regimes of
expectation
we find that this computational
construct also serve as a crucial
weighing factor in individual decision
making
so we'll see how we can put this effect
directly on decision making
regimes of
um sorry regimes of expectations have
basically a function of Fitness
enhancing social conformity
it suggests that conforming to social
norms has evolutionary advantages
it leads into a circular causality
between shared Bayesian expectations and
individual policy selection
it's consistent with findings by sanfin
2014 which emphasized the importance of
norms and expectations in Social
decision making
so now that we have
how the environment and the individual
co-construct through these regimes of
expectations
we will find how this allows us to
construct a sense of self
specifically the social self
here social norms and shared Bayesian
expectations link our individual and
collective decision making processes to
the broader understanding of selfhood
so how does active inference allow us to
model how we derive the sense of self
let's start by explaining the three main
types of cells minimal
narrative and social
the minimal self is the pre-reflexive
experience of being a subject
emphasizing the body's role in shaping
subjective experience
The Narrative self is shaped by personal
stories and experiences highlighting the
importance of generative models in
organizing these experiences
aligns with the active inference
formalism and psychological desires
providing a coherent narrative that
guides our sense of self across time
so social self emerges from interactions
with others and is influenced by social
norms values and shared generative
models
this concept is supported by the full
concept of intentionality which includes
desires beliefs intentions awareness and
skill
understanding these facets of the sense
of self through the lens of active
inference gives us an integrative
cognitive process for emotions and
social interactions
so now we'll delve more into the
intricacies of the social self
to show that the generative model and
social scripts discussed earlier are
integral to its formation
these scripts optimized through extended
active inference not only guide our
social interaction but also contribute
to the shaping of that self
creating a seamless interplay between
individual cognition and Collective
social behavior
so as we said earlier social scripts are
the cognitive blueprints that guide
individuals through a myriad of expected
actions or events in Social contexts
these scripts are essentially generative
models that help individuals predict and
navigate social interactions
they're indispensable they allow us to
continuously update our internal models
to minimize uncertainty and achieve a
stable internal States
it's particularly important in a world
where social interactions are
increasingly complex and Laden with
unspoken expectations
this optimization serves as a micro
level mechanism that complements the
macro level influence of social norms
and deontic values creating a cohesive
understanding of social behavior
social scripts can be enshrined in
Beyond to cues which enable the
environment to learn about the behavior
of its inhabitants effectively
Outsourcing the epistemic and pragmatic
values of any Behavior as we saw earlier
in cognitive Niche Construction
the context the concept of contextual
modulation integrates sensory and motor
cues to influence our actions and
decisions allowing for dynamic
adaptation and refinement of generative
models
through this modulation we can see how
social scripts and norms
are shaped and adapted over time
which promotes the adaptability in the
face of changing environments of
individuals embedded in that environment
now
contextual modulation here is pretty
important and the mechanism not only
refines our generative model but also
provides the Adaptive flexibility
required in complex environments which
unites the theoretical underpinnings of
active inference with empirical findings
and adaptive Behavior
so according to Francesco donaroma
action perception is an active
inferential process that combines motor
prediction and hypothesis testing
crucial for understanding social scripts
adaptive social behavior thus results
from the dynamic interplay of
socio-effective and socio-cognitive
processes
research by Berg Mirza provides proof of
concept that social context May alter
perception enabling more adaptive
Behavior
it's also supported by studies that
reveal how instinctive Behavior
circuits in hypothalamus dynamically
encodes spatial and sensory cues to
drive adaptive social behaviors
contextual modulation and social scripts
are integral to Adaptive behavior and
action perception
which allows us to show how social
interactions are crafted through these
different scale these deep temporal
models that integrate various kinds of
priors at different scales
so here contextual modulation acts as a
linchpin in the integration of social
scripts into the generative models
we can now appreciate how generative
model and social scripts coalesce to
form a comprehensive framework for
understanding interactions
so active inference is a nuanced lens to
explore how
power dynamics
shape share degenerative models
thereby influencing the cultural
affordances available to individuals
for instance epistemic communities
serves as platforms where power dynamics
can significantly shape shared beliefs
and actions
through the construction of certain
niche
we can see that existing power structure
lead to the creation of environments
that perpetuate these structures through
certain kinds of scripts certain kinds
of norms and through the valence that we
associate to our sense of self relative
to these Scripts
cultural affordances here are
dynamically influenced by power tinged
asymmetries
these asymmetries can affect how
individuals perceive and enact social
scripts
which further shapes the cultural
affordances that they encounter
we see how deeply intertwined cultural
affordances are with power dynamics
it allows us to understand
societal structures in more depth
so
when we expand the scope of active
inference and cultural affordance
negotiation we can dive into a case
study that of gender norms and gender
fluidity to broader cultural contexts
this exemplifies the influence of power
dynamics
so just as individuals navigate and
adapt to cultural affordances that are
deeply shaped by societal power
structures they have to navigate gender
related affordances that they also
engage with
so through this we can also understand
the concept of gender fluidity
here generative model plays specific
role which is to adapt to changing
societal norms and gender related
affordances these are cultural
performances
is dynamic from a niche construction
allows individuals to create and adapt
environments that reflect their evolving
gender identity and expression
the concept of affordance negotiation is
particularly relevant here
it refers to the process by which
individuals adapt their behavior to
maximize opportunities and minimize
challenges in their environment
in the context of gender fluidity it
involves navigating complex social
scripts and Norms that shape gender
expression
research suggests that these gender
differences in negotiation are
contextually bound and can be subject to
change
by understanding how individuals
navigate these social scripts and Norms
we can for instance address the
limitations or constraints that affects
expressions of their gender identity
so here gender through the lens of
active inference as a case study and
affordance negotiation gives us a
comprehensive view of the social
psychology and how it can apply to
gender studies for instance but this is
true for many other kinds of cultural
phenomena
so we build now on the understanding of
how active inference and power dynamics
shape cultural affordances
we can see how this allows us to
understand potentially puzzling actions
um which are shaped by social scripts
and the Dynamics within the epistemic
communities they inhabit so
we have defined how scripts allow us to
interpret different kinds of behaviors
and help people navigate these their
desired outcomes given these social
scripts
so what happens when we are faced
um with puzzling actions
people rely on their generative models
to update their beliefs and expectations
so do we interpret these behaviors based
on inherent traits or situational
reasons
here traits and motives interact with in
predicting behaviors channeling the
behavioral expression throne's life
throughout one's life on the other hand
contextual cues significantly influence
the interpretation of ambiguous
behaviors
social scripts guide our expectation in
social situations can either be adapted
when confronted with unexpected Behavior
or allow us to shift from script to
script to have a better prior over what
we might expect next
so for instance this challenge is
particularly pronounced for those who
diverge from established social norms
and script their interpretations are
influenced by the Dynamics of
information spread within their
epistemic communities
understanding ambiguous social behaviors
is not just about individual cognition
but also about the social and cultural
contexts that shape our interpretations
so now we're going to dive from this
point into the specific contextual
factors that further Nuance our
understanding
our former discussion emphasized the
influence of power and social norms and
now we're going to turn our attention to
the impact say of social anxiety
behavioral flexibility and goal-oriented
perception in shaping our
interpretations of social behavior
understanding social behaviors often
requires an approach that goes beyond
trait-based interpretations
contextual factors like social anxiety
and significantly influence how we
interpret an ambiguous social cue for
instance determining uh the most likely
prior using the most likely prior rather
than being open to other kinds of
interpretations
behavioral flexibility is another
crucial aspect to consider
it allows for adaptability and nuanced
understanding of social behaviors across
different social contexts such that a
different script A same script can be
interpreted different ways through
different kinds of behaviors
the concept of goals here plays an
important role in Social perception
they can serve to provide a broad
implication or where for where we
understand an individual to try to be
headed such that while their lower level
script may be different from the one we
have their higher level script is still
interpretable
so now we're going to try to see what
can be the outcomes in real life of all
these processes together
we're going to focus on cognitive
mechanisms that underpin social
phenomena like confirmation bias and
Echo Chambers
building on the concept of active
inference we explore how individuals not
only interpret ambiguous social cues but
also actively seek information that
confirm their pre-existing belief
thereby shaping epistemic communities
confirmation bias is a cognitive
tendency that affects information spread
and decision making
it is driven by agents seeking
information that confirms their
pre-existing belief while avoiding
challenging information
this is an effective way of using action
to minimize free energy rather than
updating beliefs in a costly manner
Echo Chambers amplify this bias by
creating self-reinforcing Loops where
individuals selectively expose
themselves to aligned information
so Research indicates that Network
structures contribute to the Persistence
of echo Chambers thereby affecting
policy making and public discourse
the minimization of free energy
transfers to the network thereby shaping
the environment
you can see here how there is a loop
where the environment both shapes the
individual who will in turn continuously
shave the environment
interestingly some Studies have
identified a reverse confirmation bias
whereby some people actually do seek out
information in an explorative manner
which again aligns with this idea of
um of active inference epistemic value
and here we may try to ponder why
certain people are more likely to break
out of their Echo Chambers rather than
uh stay in them this may align
potentially with deep temporal models
whereas we can see value at a low at um
at a
later point in time and perhaps focus
more on this expected value rather than
on the direct value of the confirmation
bias
to mitigate such biases we can use
strategies such as fostering epistemic
change through diverging information and
encouraging reflection
to break apart Echo Chambers
and now we've explored a little bit
confirmation bias and Echo chamber
we can see how this in
um extends to human communication
this allows us to explore the principles
of active inference which shape
individual cognitive Tendencies and the
influence of the broader dynamics of
communication and collective
intelligence on the environment
so we can link communicative Behavior to
biological imperative of minimizing free
energy which emphasizes the
action-oriented nature of communication
the framework allows for adaptive
Behavior even when the models deviate
from theoretical representations of the
environment
so
how do we justify that people lie or
that people
say things which don't seem to rely
properly with what everybody else seems
to believe about the environment
effectively this is an action you're
trying to push a belief onto the
environment such that there is a
potential for the environment to be
shaped in a way that evidences your
beliefs
so we can think of cognitive control
here
whereby active inference has an
effective goal maintenance in working
memory it provides top-down guidance for
overt Behavior moving beyond stereotyped
responses our understanding of
communication is enriched by introducing
neurobiologically plausible
computational hypotheses
the ecological approach to active
inference is a framework that
understand the complexities of human
communication across different scales it
explores how individuals contribute to
the collective intelligence of a group
or Society by fostering a collaborative
approach that leverages diverse skills
and knowledge
this is one of the reasons Echo Chambers
are maintained they're efficient in the
transmission of information and promote
collaboration among agents who overtly
share a model
so now we're going to look at a more
detailed understanding of ecological
dimensions of this discourse
context as we saw earlier plays a
crucial role role in the activation of
predictive inferences which offers
further support for ecological
approaches
active inference models contain terms
that encode both the object of desire
and the strength of Desire of the
psychological level
so the context of inactive inference
suggests that generative and recognition
models are best cast as realizing
inferencing control under the free
energy principle
so in this way communication through the
active inference lens gives us an
action-oriented nature of Cooperative
communication where together we mutually
craft our models such that we can
achieve a common goal
so now and lastly
let's dive into a very short overview of
how this may translate to language
processing
so remember we discussed deep temporal
models
here they enable us to explore the
sequential dynamics of language
processing
the models are hierarchical
where inference at higher levels informs
the selection of words at lower levels
this hierarchical structure allows for
the accumulation of evidence over nested
time scales
one key aspect is the emergence of
Behavioral and neurophysiological
correlates in those sequential Dynamics
like the Theta gamma couplings that we
discussed earlier it's a phenomenon that
again was observed and allows us to
measure belief updating under
variational message passing
thus generative models aren't just
predictive but also explanatory they can
help us understand neural mechanisms
like language comprehension
so in cognitive control linguistine can
be cast as individual agents
contributing to this intelligence of the
group
and the research shows that genitive
models are Central to the perception and
interpretation of the linguistic signals
we have a structural understanding of
sequences of words and their context
sensitivity
this enables the agent to resolve
uncertainty about the underlying
conceptual semantic or lexical causes of
sensory input
it can incorporate beliefs about
narratives the type of question the
scenic state of the world a semiotic
Factor indicating the topic of
discussion
these factors generate expectations for
the lower levels such as syntax and
semantics
models enable inference through this
deep structure about the narrative as
such as those seen in Reading
here the neural processes can be
understood in terms of simulating the
epistemic foraging seen in reading and
other language related activities
so to conclude
we have seen a comprehensive
understanding of active inference
inactivism and their interplay in
shaping social cognition Behavior
we have explored various philosophical
perspectives such as the inactive
affordance-based perspective The
helmholts Invasion model and highlighted
the contribution to understanding our
social interactions
we've explored deep temporal models as a
potent computational tool for modeling
complex time-dependent patterns in
social cognition such as in language as
well
we've discussed the role of mirror
neurons emphasizing their potential
sensuality in continuously updating
internal models of the environment and
their significance in social cognition
discuss potential future directions for
research if you are interested in these
topics
so here the interplay between active
inference and activism computational
models like deep temporal models give us
a multi-dimensional view of social
cognition and agency
it broadens the scope of research but
also brings us closer to our goal of
understanding the complex cognitive and
social phenomena
so for next class I offer you an
opportunity
you should pick a text
from this session from the references
that will be made available or one that
you find yourself in the literature
read it
and try to explain how it ties to the
concepts that we explored today
ideally you can present it to the group
take five minutes explain what the text
says and how it content and connects to
the contents of the course
if you have any questions we can
potentially take them out
thank you Mao that was epic
all right well people can write
questions in the chat I'll just read one
all right
where does identity and ideology fit
in my presentation or in the in the
framework that I'm presenting
so I'm gonna assume it's in the
framework
um
identity fits as a social self right
identity is literally
um how you craft your selfhood relative
to the narratives that you're given so
it's it's it's precisely the social self
that we discussed ideology corresponds
to
um a loser
let's say weak script that allows you to
shift the valence of certain values
across certain Norms so
let's assume that you understand values
as a higher or lower probability for a
type of
high-level Behavior so I value kindness
there'll be a high prior over kindness
and therefore the paths the policies
that leads to what I ascribe to as
kindness will therefore become more
likely to be adopted and will become a
norm if more of us value the same thing
the key issue here is how do I associate
the semantics of kindness to the actual
pragmatic representations and actions
that correspond to what I believe to be
kindness and this is where the
co-construction happens right we
communicate together and I'm going to
say this is kindness I'm acting on the
World to determine now this is what we
will believe to be kindness and I value
kindness very highly because that's my
ideology and therefore this is what we
should be doing all these things connect
together through the interaction of the
environment the symbols encrusted in the
environment that I share and
co-construct through communication
wow and
how does that have an impact on
affordances was the follow-up question
there
so if we go back to the part on the
course about affordances we saw that
certain
um certain things are made more likely
given the niche that you are in
um if you understand neon to cues you
see that um there's going to be some
signals that pull you as attractors in a
specific Direction
so let's assume that we have an ideology
again that promotes kindness in the
environment it is highly likely that
potential Pathways towards kindness will
be made more available
so for instance
um let's assume that we believe that
giving money to people
um is kindness there's going to be more
initiatives for you to give money so for
instance I don't know if you guys have
taken the plane recently but
um Air Canada
has started
um
program where if you have loose change
in your pockets you can put it in the in
the seat in front of you in a little
pocket thing and you put the money there
and they're going to donate it now
I'm not saying that's kindness we can
argue about the politics of it all and
the tax Etc
but this is an affordance that wasn't
there before
and now it's in my environment now I
don't have to take it but it's it's now
more readily available for me to
actually act on it and you can see this
across every level it's just that most
affordances are invisible to us as
affordances we just react to them we
just exist within them but we don't
consider they wouldn't be there such as
a bathroom in a house this is one of the
things that allows us to think more
critically about
um what it means to be homeless
like to you it seems obvious when you
need to go to the bathroom you'll go to
the bathroom right there's a bathroom
available to you but there isn't one for
people who live outside because they
don't have a home and yet we've
criminalized the act of relieving
yourself outside so we've basically said
well don't pee or if you pee well you're
now a criminal so being homeless by
virtue of not having access to the same
affordances means it's effectively
criminal to be homeless so these are the
kinds of ways that
um ideology shapes our affordances and
effectively pulls us in a state of
Attraction and effectively in in
different states of power as well
because we collectively have decided
that the only people who get to have the
the right to certain affordances are the
people who have enough money to live in
a house Etc et cetera et cetera
thanks there's a lot there all right
I'll read a comment this is something
you could address right now or save it
for the discussion or however you want
Michael wrote
would you be open to attempting to map a
social or personal narrative rather than
another element in the literature EG
translating the hero's journey or
12-step recovery
I'm not sure I'm sure I understand
attempting to map like like like like
connect the octave ontology and
formalisms to a more broadly understood
narrative or specific script
so
but
um why do we want say
um
why do we feel like the hero's journey
in itself is valuable we feel that it's
valuable because we feel that
it is a very easy explanation for uh why
somebody would have value and it is
usually
um easy to minimize free energy through
well there's a clear path right this
person wasn't the result of very complex
interactions of the environment or
whatever it's actually no no it's all
him he just understood the he understood
what he had to do he figured out what he
had to do and there you go he was able
to do it and so this
is a signal for perfect
um
Fitness to the landscape right it's Cog
it's it's it's perfect cognitive grip so
it's like
there's an underlying assumption that
this one person was able to update their
genital degenerative model sufficiently
such that they were perfectly able to
grab every affordance that the
environment gave them to go towards
their uh their state objective so in
terms of active inference it's pretty
simple it's someone that has the
capacity to go from a very unfit
generative model to a very fits
generative model relative to the
environment and so we like that
narrative because it's like okay well
then that means everybody can do it
right if if we can go from
failure to being a hero and all we have
to do is take one or two hardships and
go through it
um then then it's possible now there's
also some deification here right because
usually the hero's journey goes through
some very very difficult elements and
comes out on the other side
um and we assume that because they can
there's a rationale of meritocracy which
is
um the world is
relatively equal for everybody so it
tries to pull away from every other
power factor ecological factor and it's
like no no it's all about how you're
able to to fix your generative model to
do the right things that you have to do
um so that's why I'm not a fan of it but
I hope was this the mapping you were
looking for in terms of active inference
and um
branded immunization kind of thing
here's one thought on that the hero's
journey or
another archetypal attractor just
archetype or just
a thread that way it embeds a concise
narrative account
that is is made legible through
storytelling that we can understand and
it embodies not just kind of mythical
things but also like
real structural
implicit
features that's why some stories can be
so short and and so transferable across
context because they
abstract but also they it's what they do
include in those cases and then you
talked about how that conveys something
about value
which is what supports social norms and
social values which of course you can't
point at anywhere
yet
what can you say about what our social
norms or forces or what is the social
um what is the social
um
I think you can point to it I think you
can effectively point to processes you
can point to
material realities institutions
um
I think we tend to
use the notion of the social to
contrast it with the notion of the
individual it's just that nothing's ever
that simple
um the individual is
always built because of other
individuals so there's there's no really
such thing as an individual you're
always embedded within something so the
the real question is
what's the scale
um that you're interested in and what is
identifiable as what may be within or
without or outside of your control
within that scale and we generally
make a sort of conflation between what
is social and what is uncontrollable
even that's not necessarily true as we
saw right because we we through our
actions which can be verbal which can be
um physical like we reiterate or
push on what constitutes what is valued
by other actors within the same locality
so
um if you're asking uh what constitutes
culture
well at the level of my house culture is
uh we go to bed around 10 to 11 because
if you don't go to bed at 11 you're
gonna make noise and you're gonna wake
me up so our shared culture is this this
is something that we repeat over time
that constitutes an attractor for more
than just me
um if I look at the level of my building
it's nobody puts plants outside on their
balcony if it's at the level of Montreal
um it's there's potholes everywhere and
we're not bitching really about it we've
all accepted there's potholes everywhere
so it's part of our culture it becomes
part of our conscious
um and so why is it cultural it's
because
we can see that this
behavior these expectations translate
not just to you to your own model but it
translates to the model of other people
as well and they can expect the same for
you it's something which is uh
definitely shared so I think you can
easily point to things once you define
the scale at which it becomes manifest
thanks really interesting all right a
question from upcycle Club who wrote
in terms of the philosophical dimensions
of agency and active inference
what is the role of self-referentiality
the term but if I understand correctly
um
we saw that you have to both model
yourself and model the rest of the world
in order to understand whether your your
actions are likely to have the effects
you want to have on the world so this
self-referentiality if I understand
correctly but I could be wrong is this
notion of accurately modeling yourself
as well does that does that answer the
question
yeah all right a question from
Michael who wrote
I work with marginalized communities who
experience the larger culture as
dominant
and scientifically enabled how should
such communities fortify themselves
against the more skillful extractive
cultures
um I mean that's the
that's the main question that's been for
counter cultures forever
um
it depends what you mean by fortify
yourself
um if you mean be less likely to be
extracted from
um I think the question is being
extracted from without getting something
in return because effectively as you saw
for coordination to happen you must
provide something for the group in order
for the group to move further so it's
always a little bit extractive you will
always expand some degree of free energy
in order to move towards the policy that
you've chosen as a group so there's two
elements here chosen as a group
and there should be a return on that as
well right it shouldn't be just you pay
nobody else gives you something so it's
the degree to which the system minimizes
everybody's free energy rather than
minimizes this groups and this group is
still a high brand or Gene low
allostatic high allostatic load Etc
so what you I mean I'm not the expert on
that specifically I'm sure there are
people who have worked with marginalized
group way more than I have to give you
better insights but
from what I've read and from if I can
derive from the theory that we've
presented today it's
you need to have a strong narrative
that supports
Your Capacity to increase your Fitness
landscape
and increases and maintains the bonds
the the mark of blanket around your
group
um if your group is likely to dissolve
all the time if it's constantly
um
threatened and shaky it's not going to
be able to go very far it's always going
to be in protective mode
so you need to ensure that the group has
strong bonds that the group can expand
and that the group can together
enacts policies that lead it to
minimizing free energy and relative to
the larger group
that generally entails having more and
more connections with individuals from
the larger group such that
um
you are capable of
changing their model little by little
you want to have a strong boundary but
you don't want to be unable to
communicate with the external group
because if you do that you can't
communicate and co-construct
um so it's
it seems trivial but it's developing
Ally ships where you have people from
the larger group that become people that
adopt your message and allow the
expansion of your group and the ideology
or the generative model of your group to
be integrated within what what
determines the policies of the higher
level group or at least of the dominant
extractive group I hope I hope this
helps I know it's not as concrete as one
might want but um I'm sure people with
much more experience in these fields
would have much better answers for you
I have a question
that I've long had about some of your
different research projects which you
presented here
often there's this
modeling of both the view from the
inside with phenomenology
and also a view from the outside
so
what can you say about active inference
and that
like what
what does that mean where does that come
from
how does that matter for the personal
and the social
so imagine a marker blanket
every Mark of blanket entails there's an
outside and inside now you can always
read drawings you can always consider
it's wider smaller inside your marker
blankets there are Mark of blankets it's
all Market blankets all the way down
so this notion of internal and external
is only useful in relation to the
measurement of a joint probability
that's it
it's not
it's not ontological in the sense like
you you can I can consider that my cells
also have are have like an internal
model and an external model and I'm just
some emergent scale given the connection
between all these models that have an
internal and external model
um this group right now has a mark of
blankets which means us we have spoken
and people who have not spoken to us do
not have access to this information here
and in order to exchange information
they'll probably have to speak to some
of us and so they'll be
um
there will be an action that we put upon
the world as a group with some degree of
cohesion over time
so I think
um we have to understand internal and
external really in those terms in terms
of
temporality and objective
outside of that these are illusory
boundaries they're they they're not real
and because they're not real we can sort
of issue
um essentialism like
if a boundary can always be redrawn
relative to some kind of Observer then
everything is always Observer relative
there's and there's no such thing as a
thing which is a thing in itself it's
always relational it's always phenomenal
and how does this tie to phenomenality
well
because we are talking through this
Market blanket because we're like we we
don't actually have access to the rest
of the world except through this
boundary
the internal model is what effectively
Wiggles relative to the external world
and therefore
um you get phenomenality from this
remodeling of the external World from
this uh given boundary so for instance
our group's phenomenality of everybody
else is our shared representation of who
that even means of what that even means
we have this phenomenal
representation of that group we could
even potentially
um create
um
symbols for them we could create actual
representations which would become kind
of what would constitutes
um qualia at the level of our group so
yeah I think I've answered your question
I get lost in my thoughts sometimes but
it's great all right I'm gonna read a
comment from Abel who just requested
this comment to be read
FL wrote
I'd like to add some things about the
ideology question you have a diversity
of definitions of ideology for the
purposes of the demonstration I'll
cluster them into two one
post-structuralist in this context an
ideology is any system of value or of
instrumentation of the world this is the
definition malused in this case
everything is ideology because the basic
way we perceive the world is value
written and two structuralist
in this context an ideology is a system
of discourse that dominates a given
social context
for structuralist definitions to apply
you need a lot more than shared values
you need a clergy that maintains and
diffuses the specific discourse
underlying the ideology
I have a limited Insight in the
historical evidence but as of my
understanding ideology as factor of mass
mobilization is pretty much an early
modern particularism
I was reading
um
I mean I feel like I feel like some if
we cast it in terms of active inference
it would be um
the active States right like you need
um you need something which acts upon
the world in order to create the
self-evidencing you require and that
would be like the clergy right you need
to push these beliefs onto the world you
can't just sort of let them happen
especially if we talk about Precision
right because remember everything
Wiggles everything's always
non-stationary we move we change we
interpret we reinterpret those degrees
of uncertainty so how do we make sure
that we continue over time right that we
don't just dilute that our boundary
stays very strong that's what I was
discussing earlier with the with the
groups that want to be able to avoid
extractivism you need to proselytize you
need to make sure the same narratives we
return we always return to that same
narrative and how if we look at like
the clergy for instance
um I don't know if it was a mistake or
not but for a Time the only way to
preach was in Latin which means the only
way to access the word of God was
through these people who not only
um had to give you the word of God but
they also controlled what it meant
because you don't speak like now speak
Latin and I'm gonna believe you you you
have that knowledge so um it it goes
back to these structures of power where
there's some people that have more
access to influencing others right they
can push their beliefs with more
Precision on others and others just kind
of have to follow because they have no
real way to
themselves interpret and potentially
shift narrative themselves
when you do that I feel like I'm praying
oh there's just a lot there's a lot
there one part that I thought was very
interesting was
variational free energy is about
observations and in what you had added
just recently you talked about like the
measurement of a joint probability
there has to be like an aboutness of
sensory observations for that thing
otherwise it has not even a sensory it's
not even an inanimate thing unless it
has this
that doesn't mean it's an interesting
thing and I think that's what the recent
work
helps clarify with a sort of taxonomy
from inner to more classically active
control systems on through just
the
infinite
possibilities of broadly cognitive
modeling ecosystems of shared
intelligence yeah
I think that's a really interesting uh a
really interesting distinction you just
made so the the paper
um by Lance and Co
um
maybe that is the key because I am okay
so maybe this is a hot day but I I
generally lean towards pan psychism I do
believe that if Consciousness is the
substrate then everything is some degree
of conscious and we can stop using the
word conscious and we can use the word
model right there's a degree to which
um there's a response uh between uh the
the internal States of America blanket
in the external States so there is some
exchange of information there and
whatever's done with the exchange maybe
nothing and this may be the um the
aboutness
your internal model has no aboutness
it's just
there's information that was inputted
and the only thing that it outputs is a
constants of its boundary and that's
that's it and therefore in order to have
aboutness you have to have
the possibility for your internal States
um to shift to to move your boundaries
somehow towards something more specific
to segregates
um to to discretize the external world
into things that have more or less
valence relative to your objectives very
very akin to what Donald Hoffman is
suggesting basically
building on that and throughout your
your presentation I I got a sense of the
kind of two cultures The Sciences and
the humanities not that they were
exactly being represented in the talk
but
in terms of excellent style and
classical approach
and the non-overlapping magisteria
idea that they're sort of
a separable
technical
from the social
and it's even though it's it's widely
clear
that the the beliefs in the moment
shape the niche that has these feedback
things the development of top-down
architectures in some way that become
topped out affordances for
those or other people at some future
time
so
where do we go from there and just like
thinking about that space you know in
what how do you
how do you approach chapter six of the
textbook in terms of the recipe for the
active inference generative model
for a social setting for social setting
I think
we go from semantics
and we map the semantics
of a group and you you you qualify what
that group is maybe the description
length of that group is Extreme maybe
the description length is um my neighbor
your neighbor me and uh three of their
cats but not the fourth you know what I
mean like maybe
there's a cluster there and we map the
semantics of that group
and it's very specific
and then through those semantics there's
an inherent
um causal structures of structure of the
beliefs through which we could together
like our own little experts try to map
well okay what are our states what are
our observations how do we map to this
um and we try to test that model
and then let's assume that
um we disagree so we're gonna have
different kind of breakdowns of reality
and we're going to test the different
models in a sort of
um Bayesian expansion or ooh Asian model
reduction or just just you know testing
different models and DCM style and
seeing which one Maps better to the
expected uh observations we're going to
see given our model
um
and you can do this for anything you can
do this for a small group of neighbors
you can do this for a very large group
of people you can do this for
participants research you can do this
for medicine
um I think it's really about
how do people carve nature at its joints
and can they point to the exact
observations which they believe
um are part of the carvings or not
I think that's possible in social
sciences it's just about
taking the time to formalize how
observations
um
map to the carving together I think
social sciences generally tend to
push back
against a carving
they will prefer
something that resembles more a manifold
like it's like it it Ebbs and flows and
it's like there's some prototypical
stuff but mostly it's there's stuff that
could come in and out and stuff and
that's fine you can be accounted for so
um if you if if you look at different
carvings you can say we can work them
through on our own sort of probability
and say well this is much less likely
it's possible it fits within the carving
but it's much less likely what about
this well this is really really really
really like let's let's put a
probability on this and maybe to you the
probability is zero zero zero zero zero
zero one
that's fine it's in there
um I think they'd be more comfortable
with something that's less binary and
something that's more
um curved and allows for new things to
be added were we to disagree on
inclusions Etc
that's a great point on kind of a narrow
note but to what you just said there
let's just say that there's four options
if our prior is one zero zero zero then
the any number of evidence times zero
stays zero so that's like essentially
fixed and that's when the hyper
parameter is fixed
and then if you enable even a tiny
amount of
non-zero value and so it's like 0.99999
and then a bunch of zeros then that can
still rise off the Baseline and then
that's the whole question of attention
and cognition is how do you stay aware
of relevant Salient information
relevance realization and all that
um another point was about
um the
causal model from the outside the part
that the person doesn't directly control
there's no Direct Control in the octave
generative models of action observations
it has to go through the niche that's
how the thing is defined
and so only indirectly can observations
be changed and so that's the kind of
part that you don't have agency over
literally although the other glass half
full side is that is to the extent that
you do have agency over that
and then where that glass is and and
what narrative
actually puts water into the glass or
not and then what is the glass half full
glass half empty part
it brings so much
and just so much like on the personal
thought
size but also it's just really
interesting to see how this line of
research which was more qualitative
several years ago
like in the 2016 to 18 time and just to
see how different motifs
have come into play with the generative
models and
so it's a pretty cool lecture and many
people appreciated your work in the chat
so that's cool do you have any other
comments or anything you want to talk
about
no but uh I would um I'm gonna have to
go in about two minutes but uh I would
like to encourage people to really
participate in the next one to read some
texts
um and to to express their ideas because
this is how we we
percolates percolates this is how we
percolate good ideas and future research
and the field of social sciences is ripe
for this there's so much that can be
done right now translated connected like
we can get towards a confluent time in
research and um
and science
all right really looking forward to the
discussion and hoping that people engage
in this
affordance
thank you see ya bye